Guide to the Clement Vollmer Papers, 1898-1983
Duke University. University Archives
Clement Vollmer papers 1898-1983
Duke University. University Archives
Vollmer, Clement.
3 linear feet Extent: 1,000 Items
Clement Vollmer joined the German Languages and Literature Department at Duke University in 1926, where he remained until his retirement in 1956. In 1918, he published The American Novel in Germany. Professor Vollmer served as chair of the department during the 1950s, as president of the South Atlantic Modern Language Association, and was a member of numerous academic societies. Includes correspondence, recommendations, faculty meeting minutes, German Department memoranda, grade books and department enrollment statistics. Also includes date books, address books and diaries kept by Maude Hugo Vollmer (Mrs. Clement Vollmer). Inclusive years are 1898-1983.
UA.29.02.0105
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Clement Vollmer Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1990.
Biographical Note
Clement Vollmer was born in 1889 and grew up in Brooklyn, New York. He received his A.B. degree at Heidelberg University in Ohio in 1909 and his M.A. and Ph.D. degrees from the University of Pennsylvania in 1913 and 1915, respectively. He taught at the University of Pennsylvania for 10 years and at Cornell University for one year before joining the German Languages and Literature Department at Duke University in 1926, where he remained until his retirement in 1956. In 1918, he published The American Novel in Germany. Professor Vollmer served as chair of the department during the 1950s, as president of the South Atlantic Modern Language Association, and was a member of numerous academic societies. He also served as government interpreter in World War I and also as army and FBI consultant in World War II. Professor Vollmer died in 1972.
Collection Overview
Contains materials related to Vollmer’s career in the German Department at Duke, including correspondence, recommendations, minutes, memoranda, grade books, department enrollment, faculty appointments and wartime activities. Also includes correspondence relating to University Church services, the Academic Council and the Vigil. The rest of the collection includes address/date books and diaries (including travel diaries) kept primarily by Maude Hugo Vollmer, wife of Clement Vollmer. Also includes a list of houses (with architect names) in the Duke Forest, a New Testament, a University of Southern California handbook, a wallet full of expired oil company credit cards. Original brittle folders were replaced for preservation. Inclusive dates are 1898-1983.
Subject Headings
Duke University -- Faculty; Diaries -- American authors; Vollmer, Clement; Vollmer, Maude Hugo
Related Material
Gross (Paul M.) Papers, 1939-1979.
University Archives. Duke University.
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004.
University Archives. Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 2 Boxes
  - Class Books, Class Photo, 1920-1956 (Box 1)
  - Walter P. Baum Correspondence, 1952-1960 (Box 1)
  - German 119-120 Notes, 1927-1943 (Box 1)
  - Schedules and Rosters, 1932-1960 (Box 1)
  - German Department Enrollment, 1933-1960 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence Re: Students, 1951-1964 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1948-1968 (Box 1)
  - Department Correspondence and Faculty Meetings, 1935-1952 (Box 1)
  - 18th Century German Literature Course Materials, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Church, 1957-1972 (Box 1)
  - General Duke Correspondence, Clippings, Programs, Memoranda, 1968-1971 (Box 1)
  - Heinrich Meyer Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Dean Manchester Correspondence, 1950-1961 (Box 1)
  - Herbert Reichert Correspondence, 1955-1970 (Box 1)
  - Herman Salinger Correspondence, 1955-1970 (Box 1)
  - German Honors Program, 1936-1949 (Box 1)
  - W. Cary Maxwell Correspondence, 1936-1940 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence Re: Library, 1944-1952 (Box 1)
  - President's Office Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1)
  - F.E. Wilson Correspondence, 1940-1956 (Box 1)
  - News Clippings, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Paul Gross Correspondence and Clippings, 1949-1970 (Box 1)
  - Ziolkowski Correspondence, 1950-1971 (Box 1)
  - Warren Yates Correspondence, 1949-1958 (Box 1)
  - Wannamaker Correspondence, 1926-1949 (Box 1)
  - Graduate School Memos and Correspondence, 1935-1956 (Box 1)
  - Rev. P. Vollmer Thesis, C. Vollmer Reprints, undated, 1937, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Maude Vollmer Diaries and Notebooks, 1889-1983 (Box 2)
  - Neighborhood Information, undated (Box 2)
    Diaries, address and date books kept by Maude Vollmer, wife of Henry Vollmer, 1898-1983